<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Postscript to husbandry anatomiz'd or, an addition to the enquiry in to the present manner of ordering, dressing, and manuring the ground in Scotland for most part; whereby it is further explained and applyed, and several good effects that may follow thereupon hinted at. By the author of the first.</title>
            <author>Donaldson, James, fl. 1697-1713.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1698</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 45 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 26 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A81611</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing D1855</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R229803</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99895701</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99895701</idno>
            <idno type="VID">153177</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A81611)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 153177)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2352:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Postscript to husbandry anatomiz'd or, an addition to the enquiry in to the present manner of ordering, dressing, and manuring the ground in Scotland for most part; whereby it is further explained and applyed, and several good effects that may follow thereupon hinted at. By the author of the first.</title>
                  <author>Donaldson, James, fl. 1697-1713.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>48 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by John Reid, at his printing-house in Bell's-Wynd,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Edinburgh :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1698.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the University of Illinois (Urbana-Champaign Campus). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Agriculture --  Scotland --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:153177:1"/>
            <p>POSTSCRIPT TO HUSBANDRY Anatomiz'd OR, <hi>An Addition to the Enquiry into the preſent Manner of Order<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Dreſſing, and Manur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the</hi> GROUND in SCOTLAND <hi>For moſt Part; Whereby it is further Explained and Applyed, and ſeveral good Effects that may follow thereupon hinted at.</hi> By the Author of the firſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> Printed by <hi>John Reid,</hi> at his Printing-houſe in <hi>Bell's-Wynd</hi> 1698.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:153177:2"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:153177:3"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>Courteous READER,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>NOthing under the Sun is more the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of my Soul, than the Univerſal Good of all Men living, and for thoſe of this Kingdom in particular, being fully perſwaded of the Truth of that Maxime, <hi>No Man is born for himſelf;</hi> But the Senſe of my own Weakneſs, has long ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed my undertaking any thing in a Publick Manner, purſuant to my Inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions: But of late having maturely conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered the many miſtakes this Kingdom doth generally ly under, both in Relation to <hi>Husbandry,</hi> and ſeveral other Things, I have adventured to make an Enquiry into the Manner of Ordering and Dreſſing the Ground in <hi>Scotland,</hi> and has Eſsayed to give ſome Directions, for further Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provement thereof, and further to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain and apply what is ſaid, I have now added theſe following Sheets. The Summ
<pb facs="tcp:153177:3"/> of all that I have both firſt and laſt ſaid, doth terminat in this, That if every one would take ſuch Meaſures as eaſily they may, the <hi>Honour, Wealth</hi> and <hi>Power</hi> of the <hi>Kingdom,</hi> may in a ſhort time be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanced to double of what it is at preſent; This may ſeem a very incredible Aſserti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but at proſent I ſhall no further inſiſt in proving thereof. The Calcula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion being made already, &amp; a brief Hint given of the Means and Ways how it may be Effected: But in the mean time, (I ſay) if it be True, it is worth the noticeing, and if it be falſe, it may eaſily be demonſtrated to be ſo, Such as have any thing to object againſt what is ſaid, or would have it farther explained, I ſhall endeavour to ſatisfie. So long as I abide in Town, I ſhall attend at the <hi>Flanders</hi> Coffee-houſe for that end, betwixt the hours of 10 and 12 in the Forenoon, and 5 and 6 at Night. I could gladly wiſh every Propriator and Poſſeſſor of Lands
<pb facs="tcp:153177:4"/> in <hi>Scotland,</hi> had Copies of this Treatiſe, which you may have at the foreſaid Coffee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe, at a reaſonable Price, but to give all of you Copies <hi>gratis,</hi> my Circumſtance do not allow, neither know I any Obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation on me ſo to do. But that I may go as great a length this way as poſſible, without manifeſt prejudice to my ſelf, I ſhall leave two or three Copies of this Poſtſcript, for Publick Uſe, at every Coffee houſe in Town; And in what you can further deſire of me in Reaſon, your Commands ſhall be willingly obeyed.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Farewell.</salute>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:153177:4"/>
            <head>Poſtſcript</head>
            <p>SINCE I publiſhed theſe foregoing Sheets, I had occaſion to diſcourſe with ſeverals on that Subject, and partly have learned what Entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment they are like to meet with: Some indeed ſeem to favour my Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion beyond my Expectation, and none that I have yet met with, do diſprove of any thing I have therein propoſed, except that concerning <hi>Houſing of Sheep;</hi> And to tell the truth, any Arguments they have yet adduc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to prove their Point, are ſo far from making me alter my Opinion, that I am rather thereby confirmed in the Truth of what I have ſaid: Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſs I find <hi>I</hi> am not fully under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood by any, nor the Project receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with that Applauſe I humbly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive it deſerveth. This may ſeem a
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:153177:5"/> great peice of Vanity in me to aſſert, however I hope to make it manifeſt beyond Contraverſie: For I doubt not to aſſert by following the Meaſures, <hi>I</hi> have propoſed, the <hi>Honour, Wealth</hi> and <hi>Power</hi> of the <hi>Kingdom,</hi> may be thereby doubled at leaſt.</p>
            <p>Perhaps it may be asked, why <hi>I</hi> did not aſſert as much in the preceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Sheets? My Reaſon was, I know Landlords are generally too ſevere upon their Tenents, and if they ſee them in a thriving Condition, they either heighten their-Rent, or oblige them to remove, ſo that Farmers are altogether diſcouraged to make any Improvement whatſoever; Wherefore I thought it needleſs for me to menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Landlords profit by this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, that being a thing that he would ſee to of his own accord; And <hi>I</hi> endevoured only to ſhew in general, what benefite may be made by this Project, leaving the Landlord and
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:153177:5"/> Tenent to ſhare it betwixt themſelves. Yet in the 43 page, I gave an oblique hint at the Landlords profit, but <hi>I</hi> find General Doctrine is not the beſt; I humbly conceive, it may contribute more to the propagating of this Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, to ſpeak a little more particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly to the point, and that not only by improving of Ground, but alſo the Effects that may follow thereupon, this being a feaſible Way for making a Stock, its certain that Stock may be improven alſo.</p>
            <p>But <hi>I</hi> ſay, ſeeing Landlord and Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent muſt concur in the proſecution of what is here propoſed, both muſt ſhare of the benefite, otherwayes it cannot be expected they will unani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouſly puſh it on; Therefore in the firſt place, I would adviſe the Land<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lord to give the Tenent good ſecurity, that he nor his ſhall not be obliged to remove for ſome three, four or five ſcore years, if not to all Generations,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:153177:6"/> hereby the Tenent has Encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, to make what Improvement he pleaſeth, the benefite is his own: On the other hand, I would have the Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent obliging himſelf, and his Heirs and Succeſſors, to pay at the end of every ſeven years, one years Rent be way of Entry or Fine, over and above the yearly Rent he now payeth. I fancy at this the Tenent maketh an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer for himſelf, proteſting this is too hard for him to do; But I'm afraid the Landlord be of another Mind a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>none: However good Tenent, I would adviſe you to give the Landlord no leſs, providing you get ſecurity for continuing as above ſaid, (on other Terms I will not deſire you) And I promiſe, if you follow my Direction, you ſhall not repent it. When <hi>I</hi> deſire you to give out a Sixpence, if it bring in half a Crown, you ſuſtain no loſs: But ſo it is, every Sixpence you give out this way, ſhall profit you no leſs, after the firſt ſeven years are over.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:153177:6"/>
            <p>In the 27 page, I ſuppoſe a Farmer poſſeſſing a Room of ſixty Aikers, to have alwiſe fourty of it in Corn, on half Croft, the other half Out-field and other 20 Aikers in Graſs. <hi>By</hi> the Corn he muſt pay his Rent, for according to the common way of keeping Cattle on Dale Ground, little or no profit is had of them, as is ſhewed page 29; Now if by the profit of fourty Aikers of Corn, you are able to pay 300 Merks of Rent, then by the profit of 26 or 27, you may pay 200 Merks: Therefore leave one third of your Corn-Land Graſs, and you ſhall pay no [more but 200 Merks for the ſaid two thirds you have in Corn, unleſs I let you ſee a Viſible Way how you may get the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther third hundred Merk payed, by and attour the Increaſe you formerly had upon the ſame quantity of ground.</p>
            <p>The firſt year you leave the third of your Corn-Land Graſs, you ſave
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:153177:7"/> 13 or 14 Bolls of Grain, wherewith you uſed to ſow it; You alſo ſave the Labour of as many Aikers, which with the price of the Seed, may be reckoned as many pounds <hi>Sterling;</hi> With this Money I would have you to make an Orchyeard, as page 34: Then take the whole <hi>Dung</hi> you uſed to lay upon 6 or 7 Aikers of your Croft, and lay it upon 3 Aikers only, this three Aikers I think may be ſuppoſed to produce two <hi>Bolls</hi> more a peece, than what they did formerly, and in reſpect you are at no more Expence of Seed and Labour of an Aiker that produceth ten <hi>Bells,</hi> than if it produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced three, except Threſhing, and the Straw will do more than pay that Coſt, wherefore <hi>I</hi> reckon you ſave 6 Boils free profit on this three Aikers, this ſix <hi>Bolls</hi> 5 pound <hi>per Boll,</hi> pays 30 <hi>lib</hi> of your third hunder Merks, ſo 36 <hi>lib. 13 ſs. 4 d.</hi> remains unpayed for that year, which the Landlord ſhall ſpare
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:153177:7"/> till you can pay it with the product of the Ground. The ſecond year dung other three Aikers, on which you may alſo have two <hi>Bolls</hi> profit a peece, the firſt three Aikers continue to have two Bolls more than ordinar for four years. ſo you have twelve Bolls profit this year; which pays your third hunder Merks, except 6 <hi>lib. 13 ſs. 4 d.</hi> this added to what remained unpayed laſt year, makes in all <hi>43 lib.6 ſs. 8 d.</hi> The third year you take in other three Aikers after the ſame manner, on which ye have the like product, which makes eighteen Bolls this year, which payes the third hunder Merks, and <hi>23 lib. 6 ſs. 8 d.</hi> more, ſo nothbing remains of your by gone Rent, except <hi>20 lib.</hi> The fourth year you take in other three Aikers, on which with theſe nine already mentioned, you have 24 Bolls profit, which pays your third hunder Merks, which the <hi>20 lib.</hi> of by gone Rent, and 50 Merks more;
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:153177:8"/> Let this be laid by towards paying your <hi>Fine.</hi> The fifth year dung that which you dunged the firſt year, and ſo continue to go over the four parts of your Croft Succeſſively. The three years that are yet to expire before the end of the ſeventh year, you have 24 Bolls profit <hi>per annum</hi> on yar 12 Aikers of Croft, whic yeeldeth 80 Merks a year more than your third hunder Merks, three time 80 and the 50 Merks laid by the fourth year, is 290 Merks, which payeth your <hi>fine</hi> all to 10 Merks, and to pay this 10 Merks with, you have all the profit of your Orchyeard, the Roots and Kail you have in it, may be more profitable than ten Bolls of Grain for your Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily, which may be reckoned fiftie pounds; The Flay of an Aiker and half, may be worth eighteen poiunds. A Crown a peece of twelve Sheep keeped on the Stuble of your Orch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yeard, is 36 pounds. Honey worth
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:153177:8"/> 24 <hi>lib.</hi> this in all makes 123 <hi>lib.</hi> And when your Fruit-trees grow up, you may have as much profit of them, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide the <hi>Out-field</hi> all this while will be growing better by degrees, as well as your Croft, ſo that by this time you may have a Boll <hi>per</hi> Aiker more on it than ordinar: And your Grafs being both better, and much more of it, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viding you obſerve the Direction given page 38, You may make 200 Merks profit of your Cattle. Moreover, your Ground is but begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to be brought to a good Conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, you can not expect it will be as good with once or twice Dunging, as afterwards it may be: <hi>Will either Man or Beaſt that is lean, be made fat by a Meal or two.</hi> I do not think in leſs than 24 or 30 Years, the Ground can be brought to ſo good a Condition as afterwards it will be; <hi>And Tenents get not long Tacks, never think they will Improve it for other Men:</hi> But even
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:153177:9"/> from the beginning, you ſee there can be profit made abudance, to encour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age any body to let about it. To be Brief, I deſire not to reckon every thing narrowly that may be made of it, leaſt the Landlords grudge; But I offer to make it evident, to the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viction of any Reaſonable Man, That Farmers following this Method, ſhall be inabled to pay their Landlords all that I have ſpoken off, and ſhall have more profit by farr, than they can have by following the preſent way. Tho they did not pay one Sixpence, for when all the above mentioned pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits may be made without Hedging or Incloſures, what profit may be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected when that pains is taken, and Manure extraordinar provided, as pag. 72, beſide many other peeces of Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provement. Now if this be true, as I am perſwaded it is, then has the Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent as much Gain, as if he had his Room for nothing at all; And it is
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:153177:9"/> not one Tenent, or ten or hundered, that receiveth this Benefit, but all and every one through out the whole Kingdom may have this profit; I do not mean every indevidual Farmer may make a like Advancement in their profits, for in ſome places the Ground may be ſo much improven, that triple ptofit may be thereof made at leaſt; Other places cannot ſo well be advanced above one third part, but complextlie conſidered, I am per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded that the whole of it may be doubled. Therefore I conclude, Far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers in proſecution of this <hi>Project,</hi> ſhall be as great Profiters, as if they had another Kingdom equal to this beſtowed them <hi>Gratis,</hi> providing they changed not their <hi>Ancient Cuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom;</hi> And the Heritors or Propriators of Lands, are ſo farr from being at any loſs, that they reap a ſeventh part more Benefit than at preſent they do, beſide their preſent Rent is ſecured,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:153177:10"/> ſo that it is moſt viſible, that the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritable Stock of the Kingdom, may be more than doubled.</p>
            <p>Now If a poor Man that cannot guide himſelf, may be permitted to direct othets, I'le ſhew you how the Moveable Stock, may be as much in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſced, and then I hope my aſſertion is proven. Landlords to you now I direct my Diſcourſe, Perhaps ye may grudge, I allow nothing but a ſeventh part, where the Tenent has ſo much; The Truth is, Tenents have but a ſorrie Life of it, as Matters go at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, and they had need of the greateſt ſhare of the profit, beſide, they are at all the pains, &amp; run all the Riſque, for tho they ſhould not make all the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit I propoſe, ſtill are they obliged to pay you; But I ſay more, You may accept of Little, where you could ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect nothing at all: I ſuppoſe your Predeceſſors and your Selves, have taken the beſt Meaſures you can to
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:153177:10"/> advance your Rent, and more than it is at preſent you could never make it. Now if I ſhall lay down a way, how ye may advance it a ſeventh part, (which I dare almoſt promiſe in name of all the Farmers in <hi>Scotland,</hi> provid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing you gave them long Tacks) then have you ſo much Gain ye could never expect, and ſeeing their profit is not your Loſs, you have no Cauſe to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy them; But what if I make it appear this Fine, atithe end of every ſeven years, ſhall be more beneficial to you, than one third part more every year: Tis like ye may call this a Maggot, but let me be heard before I be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned.</p>
            <p>Commonly all People live according to their Rent, whether it be little or much, he that has 5000 Merks <hi>per annum,</hi> may have as much free Monie at the Years end, as he that hath ten or twentie: So I ſay tho you had a third mote Rent, ye would perhaps find
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:153177:11"/> way to get it diſpoſed of, as well as what you have; Yea, but ſay ye, then we would live ſo much the better or more ſplendid: 'Tis a Queſtion if ye would, for ye had better have an hundred Pounds well payed, as an hundred and twentie promiſed, when the Tenents are not able to pay it punctually at the Term. but this one running on in Arrier half a Years Rent, the other a whole year, and a third two Years, and ſome breaking now and then amongſt hands, and Factors Accompts running on in Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion, ſo that its very hard to redd Marches with them: And in the mean time; when you might have your Monie, to beſtaw to the beſt Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage ye could, you are obliged to run in Merchants Accompts, with many other diſadvantages: I doubt not but an hundred Pounds punctually payed, is better than an hundred and thirty pay'd after this faſhion. Beſide all this
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:153177:11"/> a Gentleman getting the name of ſo much Rent, he muſt keep a Table and Retinue, anſwerable thereunto. From all which Diſadvantages he is obliged to burden the Heir, for the providing Portions to the reſt of his Children, and that lyeth on his Shoulders from Father to Son, till taht Familie be extinct, or elſe the reſt of his Children are ſo meanly Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided for, that they cannot live any way ſuteable to their Station, and they being too gentle to learn, or fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low anie honeſt Imployment, muſt ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther go abroad to puſh their For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes, or go up and down the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rrey like Vagabonds, this is the Caſe with many: But if it be ſaid, this is not the Caſe with all, I ſhall readily confeſs that, but that needs not hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der me to give my Advice to others, neither can they be the worſe to hear it: But I ſay by this Project, even theſo that are in the worſt Circumſtances,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:153177:12"/> ſhall have the Rent that now they have the Name of, well payed, tho at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent it be otherwiſe, and ſhall have all their Children honeſtly provided for, without burdening the Heir a ſixpence, and to make this the more plain, I ſhall meke a Suppoſition, thus.</p>
            <p>I ſuppoſe a Young Gentleman ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding to his Fathers Eſtate, in the twentie or twentie firſt Year of his Age, the Tacks of his Tenents are half run, ſo in the twentie fourth year of his age, the <hi>Entery Money</hi> and <hi>Graſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum</hi> due be his Tenents, is payed to him, I ſuppoſe his Yearly Rent to be 5000 Mer, the <hi>Fine</hi> he now receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth is juſt ſo much, this is all ftee profit, for if his Tenents had followed their old way fo Labour, this he could not expect, and now his Yearly Rent is entire beſide this; Wherefore I would have him lay this 5000 Merks by for his eldeſt Child, except the Heir, which perhaps is not born for half a dozen Years to come; I would
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:153177:12"/> have him count it Sacriledge to medle with it, but let the Intereſt thereof be gathered for the Child's Uſe, and before the Child be Marriageable, it may be doubled if not tripled. In the 31 Year of his Age, he hath another <hi>Fine</hi> payed him, which may be laid up for another Child; In the 38 Year of his Age, another <hi>Fine</hi> falleth due, lay this by for a third Child; In the 45 Year of his Age, as much for a fourth Child, in the 52 Year, as much for a fifth Child, and in the 59, a Portion for a ſixt Child: This before he be ſix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie Years of Age, he has Reaſonable Portions provided for ſix Children, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide the Heir, if he have fewer, he may give each of them a <hi>Fine</hi> as is ſhewed and divide the Superplus a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them; If he have more, (as very few hath,) then he may get the reſt more eaſily portioned, that theſe are provided for already. But ſay ye, Perhaps before the Father exceed fifty Years, his Eldeſt Son may be married,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:153177:13"/> and ſo long as the Father applyeth this <hi>fine,</hi> for the Uſe of his own Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, the Son cannot have it for the Uſe of his; Such a thing may fall our, but its as probable, the Father will not have ſo many Children, as what <hi>I</hi> have ſuppoſed, and if he have not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove 5, that which is appointed for his ſixth Child, may be ſettled on his <hi>Oey,</hi> but make it as ye will, 'tis better to have ſo many provided for, as none at all.</p>
            <p>But ſay ye, all this is not ſo good as another third more Rent, for we can be our own Stewards, and live more ſplendid, and tho we lay but one half of that third part more additional Rent by every Year, we may there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with provide our Children more plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifully, than what is propoſed.</p>
            <p>But ye would conſider, if ye had a third more Rent than what ye have, it would be expected you ſhould live accordingly, and if ye do it not, ye
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:153177:13"/> will be reckoned Miſers; And beſide when your Rents are ſcrewed to the higheſt. you cannot have them punc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually payed, and ſo run in all the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conveniences above ſaid: Wherefore I'm of Opinion, tho you had 10000 <hi>lib:</hi> a year, you cannot ſo eaſily lay 500 up for your Childrens Uſe every Year, as you may lay this <hi>fine</hi> by, every ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven Years once. But ſay ye one Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent payeth his <hi>fine</hi> this Year, another the next, ſo we get not all in one Year. therefore we are at the ſame pains in gathering of it, as if we had only ſo much more Yearly Rent. To which <hi>I ſay,</hi> I would have you order it ſo, that you may have it all to come in at oncs, and tho ſome of your Tenents ſhould begin to ſet about this New Method at one time, and others at an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, when the time comes that the firſt are to pay their <hi>fines,</hi> rather tako from theſe that have begun laſt, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portionable to the Years they have
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:153177:14"/> followed this Method, and enter them altogether, as take it in by parſells, for I am apt to believe it will not do ſo well, to come in at ſeveral times.</p>
            <p>Perhaps ſome may object, if every Landlord follow. this Method, all will have Money. to lend, and none will need to borrow, therefore it will be impoſſible to get all this great Stock; put to any profitable Uſe.</p>
            <p>I wiſh it were come that length, to have more Stock than we know how to diſpoſe of, but ſince ye have had patience to hear me hitherto, be pleaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to hear my Anſwer to this alſo.</p>
            <p>By the Proſecution of this Project; I ſhewed page 32 and 33, a great dale of people may be ſpared, that are now imployed in Tieling and Dteſſing the Ground, except they be imployed in making Incloſures, and even tho ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny be ſet to that kind of Work, there will be abundance notwithſtanding to labour in <hi>Manufactures;</hi> There is no
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:153177:14"/> doubt, if people apply themſelves, in good earneſt that way, <hi>Manufactures</hi> of all kinds may be much propagated in a ſhort ſpace: For want of Stock, that great obſticle, being removed, all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Letts may be eaſily overcome: Now, if every individual Propriator of Lands throughout the whole King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, may have a Years Rent everie ſeventh Year, beſide his ordinar Rent, <hi>What vaſt Stock will this make in all?</hi> Four hundered thouſand pounds <hi>Star<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting,</hi> and even but a part of that is thought ſufficient to advance our <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frican Trade:</hi> And I ſuppoſe one Years Rent of all the Lands in <hi>Scotland,</hi> may be four or five times as much: What great Trade of <hi>Fiſhing and Land Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nufactures</hi> may be thereby carried on? And how much the more, conſidering 'tis not only ſo much <hi>Stock</hi> advanced at firſt; But infallibly this may be renew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed everie ſeven Years; And how much this may promot the <hi>Honour, Powet,</hi>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:153177:15"/> and <hi>Wealth of the Kingdom,</hi> according to my weak Judgement, may be more than can be eaſily credited, untill the event prove it; I doubt not but with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in 24 or 30 Years, the Moveable Stock of the Kingdom may be tripled, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out going to Forraign Plantations to ſeek Wealth, or digging in Mines for Ore. By this project everie Man may digg. Treaſure out of his own Field, for by obſerving the Meaſures propoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, both Cattle and Grain may be greatly increaſed, ſo that we may both live more plentitullie, and have much thereof to export, beſide the uſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Advantage of <hi>Manufactures:</hi> And that which makes this project the moſt feaſible of all others, is, That one needs no Dependance on another; ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept betwixt Landlord and Tenent, and there is more Hopes to bring two to one mind than a great Society of people. I may take my own Meaſures in Ordering and Dreſſing my own
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:153177:15"/> Ground, whither others do the like or not. But in many other projects, there muſt be a concurence of a Mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude, and perhaps the Managers ſometimes prove not ſo faithful to all concerned as could be wiſhed, but in this it is otherwayes. And another ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage in this project. there is no Riſque to run, the worſt that can befal, no loſs can be ſuſtained by the Undertakers, wherefore I conclude, if this be not ſet about, we need to try none other whatſomever.</p>
            <p>To anſwer all Queries and Objecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons that may occur, about this project would take more Room than can con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniently be allowed here, therefore I refer that work to another place. But in the mean time, I ſhall anſwer ſome few, which I judge may be moſt material; Perhaps it may demanded, <hi>What kind of Manufactures can be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagated in this Kingdom:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To which I ſay; <hi>All ſorts whatſoever:</hi>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:153177:16"/> For I know no Reaſon why that can not be wrought here, that can be fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhioned or performed with Mens Hands in any place of the World, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viding we have the ſame Materials, and were bred too, and taught in theſe ſeveral Arts and imployments, and in no place without both of theſe, can any thing be performed, and even tho we ſtand want Materials, of the things we ſtand in need of, ought to be made or compoſed; We may get theſe things unprepared, much cheaper than the made Work.</p>
            <p>We have two univerſal Objections againſt everything that can be ſaid in perſwadidg us to any thing we have not been accuſtomed to. If it be ſaid our Ground may be improven, and the more to convince us of this, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance the Example of others. It is an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, our Ground is naturally more barren than other Kingdoms; If we be deſired to ſet about any Handy
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:153177:16"/> Labour, then our Water is ſo bad; that therewith we can neither Dye, Bleach, make Hats, nor Mill Cloath,</p>
            <p>To the firſt I ſay, if our Ground be bad, we take the wrong way to make it better, for the beſt Ground in <hi>Europ,</hi> being uſed as commonly ours is, ſhall in a ſhort time grow little better than our own, for ſo long as it will bear Corn, we plough it over and over, till the product can ſcarce deſray the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence of Seed and Labouring, and then we give it a ſmell of Manure only, or elſe leaves it Graſs a Year or two, and as ſoon as it begins to gather a Soard, <hi>up the red ſide of it again,</hi> ſo that in ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect they will neither let it bear Graſs nor Corn.</p>
            <p>Now ſay <hi>I,</hi> behold how much our next Neighbours in <hi>England</hi> manage their Ground to advantage more than we do? Your Anſwer is, Their Soil is Naturally better, and their Climat
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:153177:17"/> warmer. What is your inferrence? For notwithſtanding the Fertillity of their Soil, and warmneſs of Climat, they think it neceſſarie to plant Hed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges to keep it warmer, as page 64. And alſo they find it for their Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage, to make but a fourth or fifth part of their Ground Corn at once, becauſe they cannot get all of it ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently keeped in Manure. But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe our Ground is more barren, and Climat colder, therefore we need not uſe Means to reſtrain External Cold, and may alwayes have one half, or two third parts of it in Corn. Is this your inference? Well, good enough, I think it needs no Anſwer.</p>
            <p>To that Objection anent the bad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of our Water, I would fain ask a Queſtion, which may ſerve for an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to to this, Do ye think the bad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of our Water has any Influence upon a Man working in Iron or Wood, that his Workmanſhip is not ſo good
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:153177:17"/> perhaps as elſe where it may be had?</p>
            <p>Then ſay ye the people in this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom muſt be much duller than others, and therefore they can never attain to the like Dexterity in any <hi>Curious Art,</hi> or <hi>Mechanick Operation,</hi> with theſe of other places.</p>
            <p>This <hi>I</hi> will be very loath to grant, for the contrar I firmlie believe, but indeed I will confeſs, That commonly our <hi>Mechanicks</hi> are not ſo Dexterous or Expert as others; But the Cauſes may be one or all of theſe. <hi>Firſt,</hi> We have not the Inſtruction or Edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of ſeveral others, and can it be expected a Man that has not been Taught or Inſtruſted in ſuch or ſuch an <hi>Art,</hi> can be an equal Proficient to him that has had that Help, providing they are of equal parts, take a Man of any of theſe Nations you pretend are moſt Expert and capable of Inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and put him to do a peece of Work he never did or ſaw done, can be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:153177:18"/> it as one that is experienced with that ſort of Labour? <hi>Secondly,</hi> It is the Vulgar Opinion, <hi>Nothing that is made within the Kingdom, can be ſo good as that which is brought from Abroad,</hi> Nor will they give ſo much for it, altho it be really better, ſo the Seller know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing he cannot have a price for it, if he ſhould beſtow Labour upon it, makes it his Study how to affoord his Ware cheap, ſeing the Buyers will not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow a price upon good Ware, and that only becauſe <hi>it is our own Home ward Making.</hi> Another Cauſe why our <hi>Mechanicks</hi> are not ſo Dexterous as per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps others are, is, They abide not cloſs at one kind of Work, but from one thing to another, ſo that they can't be ſo expert in ſeveral things as they might, and undoubtedly would be in one thing: But in may other places, <hi>Mechanicks</hi> abid cloſs at one ſort of Work, ſo that they become not only expert as to the making of the Work
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:153177:18"/> good, but alſo a far greater quantity of it; <hi>I</hi> remember <hi>I</hi> heard a Nailer, that's a Nail-maker tell. He knew a Man that was accuſtomed to work in nothing but Sparrowbills, a ſort of ſhort Nails wanting heads, he uſed to make a very conſiderable number of them, he ſaid to the number of 7 or 8 thouſand a day. and yet if he had been ſet to make common Nails, he neither could make them good, or any conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable number of them: I doubt not but a Man abiding ſtill at one kind of Work, may both attain to a greater Dexterity in making of it fine, and do much more of it, than another that from one thing to another, is continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>allie turning.</p>
            <p>But ſayes ſome, We have had Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chanicks from abroad, and we have tryed to make ſeveral things, and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly Hats, and Broad Cloath in this Kingdom, and yet we cannot make our Ware ſo good, as what we can have from abroad.</p>
            <pb n="34" facs="tcp:153177:19"/>
            <p>Who knows whether theſe Forraign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers be the moſt expert of their Imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, in theſe places from whence they came, or perhaps they may be ſubborned to conceal the Art of their Calling, or perhaps their Maſters find it not for their Advantage, to beſtow the Expenſe that is required in making the fineſt Ware, becauſe we have ſuck'd in that Tenet, <hi>It cannot be fine enough, if it be our own homeward making.</hi> Moreover tho there be ſome few skil'd in theſe Imployments to direct, yet they cannot do all the Work with their own hands, and till theſe that aſſiſt them, come to ſome meaſure of Dexterity, it cannot be expected their Ware can be ſo good, as otherwiſe it may be. Theſe that would propogat any new Manufacture, muſt lay their Accompt to labour under ſeveral Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>advantages at firſt; For inſtance, when Sope Manufactures were firſt ſet up in this Kingdom, their Sope was not ſo good as what we had from abroad by
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:153177:19"/> far; Theſe at <hi>Glaſgow</hi> gave it over, as a thing they could not accompliſh, theſe at <hi>Leith</hi> continued to work on, and now have acquired ſo much know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge in that Art, that their Sope is better than that we have brought from abroad; From whence I conclude, if theſe in <hi>Leith</hi> had given over, as theſe at <hi>Glaſgow</hi> did, it had been thought our Water in this Kingdom was ſo bad, that Sope could not be therewith made, whereas we ſee the Falſhood of that Conjecture: My Opinion is, that what ever any may object againſt Water in other Caſes, its altogether groundleſs.</p>
            <p>I ſhould think if Strangers were en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged to ſet up here for themſelves, or ſome of our own Countrey Men ſent abroad, to be inſtructed in the knowledge of theſe Arts, wherein we have leaſt <hi>Knowledge,</hi> it might be a Mean to propagat Manufactures; And eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially Fiſhing and Woolen Manufac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, might prove to the Kingdoms Unſpeakable Profit, if they were pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moted:
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:153177:20"/> Yea there is no kind of Art or Imployment, but what we might ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire Knowledge in, if we had Means of Inſtruction; And becauſe formerly the great Cauſe of our living at home in Penurie, was Povertie and Want of a Stock, once to ſet about any Fru ga litie (for a poor Man is ſtill keeped poor, becauſe he has nothing once to put him in Capacitie to do for himſelf) I ſay by this Project that Maladie is removed, and we are put in a Capaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie to propagat Manufactures, build or buy Ships, and do many other things that may advance the <hi>Honour, Pouer</hi> and <hi>Wealth</hi> of the Kingdom.</p>
            <p>But ſayes ſome, Fine Cloath cannot be made here, becauſe our Wool is courſe; Grant it is, We may buy as much Wool, as may be ſour Ells of Cloath, for the price of one Ell, and beſide if our Sheep were keeped, as is propoſed Chapter 5, our own Wool may be much improven, then we ſave the other three parts of the Expence, it
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:153177:20"/> would coſt ns. I know it will not be for a fourth part of the price to the Wearer, but I mean the fourth part of the Money or Ware, that is exported furth of the Kingdom, to bring home Cloath may be ſaved, and a great dale of People, that are at preſent imploy'd in Tovling their Lives out, working in the moſt induſtrious Way that can be invented to run out the Ground, may be imployed in making the ſaid Cloath, and other profitable Imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; And becauſe I told you, I had met with ſome Oppoſition, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the way of Stock keeping I have propoſed, I ſhall let you hear the moſt material Arguments, any have yet adduced to prove the contrar.</p>
            <p>Some acknowledge <hi>Houſing of Sheep,</hi> may be practicable in a few, but not in great numbers, others foreſecing, grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the firſt, is the high way to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn the latter, manfully diſpute againſt both, the ſtrength of their Arguments are theſe, viz: To put Sheep in houſes,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:153177:21"/> makes them ſcab, and the great diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty of getting Litter or Bedding to them, and alſo the Expence of build-Hutts will be great.</p>
            <p>To the firſt <hi>I</hi> ſay, if it be true, then <hi>I</hi> confeſs its a very pungent Objection, and becauſe ſome bring in matter of Fact as a proof, I ſhall ſhow what I know of Matter of Fact to the contrar, I have known 5 or ſix ſcore ſheep, for a dozen or ſixteen Years together, put in Hutts every Night, and not one of them was ſcabbed, during that time; Now if a hundred can be lodged ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniently, as may prevent this bad ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, then a hundred thouſand may al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo be preſerved the ſame way, provid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the like Care and pains be taken on every hundred of them. But <hi>I</hi>'ll tell you where the Miſtake lyeth. Some Stock-keepers that have tryed the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periment, to ſave a little Expenſe in building Hutts, have crammed them ſo throng, that one could not conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently ly beſide another, neither
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:153177:21"/> did they take Care to have them lying clean and dry, from whence this bad Effect followed: When I deſire a Man to hold out of a Mire on his Right hand, I bid him not leap into a Ditch on his Left, when I complain of letting Sheep ly out wanting Food, amongſt Froſt and Snow, page 94, <hi>I</hi> do not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire they ſhould be uſed after this faſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but page 97, I recommend build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Hutts ſo large, that the Sheep may ly at eaſe, and have free Air, and page 99, by all means to lay them clean and dry.</p>
            <p>Others ſay, when they buy Cattle to put in their Parks, for fatning theſe that are accuſtomed to ly without, take on fleſh much ſooner than theſe that have been houſed.</p>
            <p>To Anſwer this diſtinctly, I will give you this Similitude; Let a <hi>High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land Man</hi> that is accuſtomed to go through Bogs and Glens, with only a looſe Plaid about his Body, his But<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tocks altogether bare, and his Brogues
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:153177:22"/> that defend him not from one drop of Water. Now I ſhall readily believe, this Man in the beginning of a Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pine, ſhall endure more Hardſhip than another that has been accuſtomed to good Keeping and warm Cloathing; Yet I ſhall ſcarce be perſwaded to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low his Example. No doubt Cattle that accuſtomed to ly in a warm houſe, will not at firſt agree ſo well to ly without in a Park, as other accuſtom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed thereunto; But let them be put in a houſe all night, and feed with the other all day, I doubt not but they may be as ſoon fat as the other.</p>
            <p>Now to the building of Sheep Cots, I ſay, if Stones can be eaſily had, you may make the walls of ſtone, if not, Sods or Turffs may ſerve, the form I judge moſt convenient, and leaſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſive, is a ſquare of 50 foot each way, 4 foots in hight will be enough, then within this build another wall ten foot from the other, the inner ſquare is 30 foot in length each quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:153177:22"/> but in ſtead of this inner wall, let there be only pillars made for the ſupport of your Roof: The Reaſon why I recommend leaving one ſide of the Houſe open, is to let the Sheep have Air, but if the ſide of a ſingle houſe were left open in all Weather, it could not defend from Storm and Snow; The breadth of your Houſe being only the diſtance betwixt the inner and outer wall, <hi>viz:</hi> ten foot, Cuples of 7 or 8 foot length may ſerve, and in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard they are ſhort, they will not need to be very thick, about the thick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of good Care polls may ſerve, which being placed at 6 or 7 foot diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, about 30 Cuples will ſerve the whole Square. The outer wall of 50 foot each ſide, being builded of Sods, or with ſome few Stones mixed with the Sods, will not coſt above ten Shil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings of Expence, the Cuples may be had I ſuppoſe for ten pence a pair, which is 15 pounds, ſmall Sticks will ſerve for Cabers or Ribbs: But geant
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:153177:23"/> they are as dear as the Cuples, both make but 30 pounds, ſay the Thatch coſt as much as the walls, all make but 42 pounds, and this Square will contain 12 or 15 ſcores of Sheep with eaſe: But call them but 12 ſcore only, the Expence is but 3 <hi>ſs. 6 d.</hi> for every Sheep, not the price of two years <hi>ſmear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing;</hi> This Houſe keeped in Thatch, may laſt 30 Years, and the Thatch I reckon nothing at all, for grant you put Divets on it every two Years once, they are worth all your pains for Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nure.</p>
            <p>As to the beding of your Sheep, I ſay, if ye have Corn, as is ſuppoſed page 100, ye have Straw enough for that uſe, if not, Ruſhes, Bent, dry Sand, or any thing that may keep them dry and clean will ſerve; But if none of theſe things can be had, then can you not want Divets; And becauſe this is the moſt expenſive, I ſhall reck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on how farr your profit may go be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond your Coſt in this. A Man may
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:153177:23"/> cut or caſt ten Cart load of Divets in a day, that is ſix pence, ſay the drying and bringing of them home coſt twice as much, you have them cheaper than two pence a Cart, every Cart of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vets, will be 2 or 3 of Dung, becauſe the Piſs and Dung, add both to the weight and bulk, the Cart of Dung is worth 14 pence, as was ſhewed Chap. 5. When your Sheep begin to ly any thing wet, lay a new courſe of Divets over the whole floor, with the green ſide up, or if you have Straw or Ruſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, ye may bed them whiles with the one, and whiles with the other; The profit you have by this Labour, is more than ye readily can believe, for your Sheep being provided in Food, and preſerved from cold and wet, they are in a much better Condition, Eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially that time of the year, when they are with Young; And I am of Opinion, that any Creature receiving wholeſome and plentiful Nouriſhment,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:153177:24"/> when it is in the womb, is thereby more ſtrengthened, and brought to a wholeſome Conſtitution, than by any ſo long time feeding, during the time of its Life; And tho ſeverals of our Stock-keepers may feed their Cattle prettie well in Summer yet very few provide for them in Winter, as the Schamles can bear Witneſs.</p>
            <p>Perhaps it may be ſaid, theſe Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vats being cut upon the Paſture, will ſpoil a great dale of Ground. To which I ſay, you cannot in Reaſon expect much Benefit, but you muſt be at ſome loſs; I do not propoſe this as a thing that may be done without any Coſt at all, but I endeavour to make it evident, that your Profit ſhall be more than your loſs; And if you will conſider the Benefit your other Ground receiveth by the Sheep Dung, you'll find all the prejudice ye ſuſtain by the loſs of ſo much of your Paſture fully repayed with Intereſt.</p>
            <pb n="45" facs="tcp:153177:24"/>
            <p>To inſiſt in ſpeaking to every thing that may be for the further explaining and applying of the whole Project, and touching of many things concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Husbandry,</hi> I have not yet ſpoken to all, would take up thrice as much as all I have yet done: And to be plain, I have no great inclination to engage my ſelf in the Expence that will be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired to finiſh ſuch a Work, until I ſee further what Entertainment that which I have done already meets with. I have ſaid as much as I can in few words, and for ought <hi>I</hi> know, am the firſt in this Kingdom that has eſſayed any thing on this Subject. But I'm of Opinion, there may be ſeveral Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections given, concerning the Order<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Dreſſing the Ground, more uſeful to the Inhabitants of <hi>Scotland,</hi> than what has yet been propoſed by any that ever wrote upon <hi>Husbandry.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I know ſeverals have written per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps as well as any Man can in general
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:153177:25"/> But none of theſe being particularly acquainted with the Nature and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of Ground in this Kingdom, nor with the particular miſtakes the people generally ly under, their Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections cannot ſo exactly anſwer our Caſe. A skilful <hi>Phyſician</hi> may prepare <hi>Phyſick</hi> or <hi>Medicine,</hi> very good for ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Diſeaſes; And yet a farr leſs ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhed <hi>Phyſician,</hi> may prepare Phyſick that is fitter for the parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular uſe of one whoſe Conſtitution and Diſeaſe he knoweth: I doubt not but particular Directions may be given in Relation to <hi>Husbandry,</hi> more exact to our Caſe than any yet propoſed by Strangers. Ploughing too much of the Ground, Leaving it without Fence, And overlaying their Paſtures: Theſe three being the grand Miſtakes Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ly moſt under, I have endeavour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to perſwade them to Reformation therein, which is a quite other <hi>Theam,</hi> than is uſually inſiſted on by others.</p>
            <pb n="47" facs="tcp:153177:25"/>
            <p>But before I cloſe, I ſhall take notice to one Objection, that perhaps may ſeem of great Moment to many, and yet in Reality is of no force at all; The thing here propoſed is very great, <hi>viz: That if every one would take ſuch Meaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ures, as eaſily they may, the</hi> Honour, Wealth <hi>and</hi> Power <hi>of the Kingdom, may ſoon be advanced to the double of what it is at Preſent;</hi> The Means by which ſo great a Matter is to be accompliſhed, being ſo eaſie and very common, (whereas the Means for proſecuting ſo great a Work, would be expected to be very wonderfull and extraordinar) therefore no ſuch Effect can follow the proſecution of this Project.</p>
            <p>How weak ſo ever the Means are, to me they ſeem to prove effectual if followed, and if the Calculation made already, ſerve not to perſwade you to the like thoughts, I muſt know your Objections before I can ſatisfie you: But it is not the firſt time great Things have been accompliſhed by weak Means,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:153177:26"/> and the leſs that can be expected from the inſtrument or Means, there ſeems to be the more of an Overruling Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence in it; And to tell you my own thoughts, ſeveral Providences ſeem to concurr in the proſecution of this Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, <hi>viz:</hi> The long continuance of the Froſt, which doth oblige People to a Complyance (for this year) to one ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial Point I have propoſed: To witt, <hi>To take leſs Ground into Tillage, and keep'd in better Condition.</hi> And then again by this, a great dale of Seed may be ſaved, which will come very ſeaſonably this Year: In reſpect of our-preſent Scar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city of Grain. And now beſide, upon the Concluſion of a Peace, People may apply themſelves thereto the more ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectually, together with ſeveral other Things that <hi>I</hi> have not Room here to inſert.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:153177:26"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
